It was the end of October in the mountains in Austria.
10월 말 오스트리아의 산에서 있었던 일입니다.
I was there on a field trip with my architecture students from Zurich.
취리히 출신의 건축과 학생들과 견학 중이었지요.
And when we reached a high valley,
우리가 어느 깊은 협곡에 도착하고 나서야
I surprised them with the news that there was no hut
저는 하룻밤을 머물 민박도 호텔도 예약해놓지 않았다고
or hotel booked for the night.
학생들에게 말했습니다. 모두가 놀랐지요.
It was not a mistake.
실수가 아니었습니다.
It was totally on purpose.
저에게 계획이 있었죠.
The challenge was to build our own shelter with whatever we could find.
저는 학생들에게 주변 재료로 묵을 공간을 만들어보자고 했습니다.
And we all survived.
결국 우리 모두 해냈습니다.
It was cold, it was really tough ...
아주 추웠고, 매우 어려운 일이었지요.
and it was a great learning experience
하지만 많은 것을 배울 수 있는 기회였습니다.
to discover that there are a lot of resources given by nature for free,
자연은 우리에게 많은 자원을 공짜로 제공한다고 알게 되었고
and all that we need is our sensitivity to see them ...
우리에게 요구되는 것은 필요한 자원을 발견하는 민감성과
and our creativity to use them.
그걸 잘 활용하는 창의성이었습니다.
I found myself in a similar situation.
저에게도 비슷한 경험이 있었습니다.
When I was an architecture student about 13 years ago,
13년 전 제가 건축과 학생이었을 때
I went to Bangladesh to a remote village called Rudrapur
방글라데시의 외딴 마을인 루드라푸르라는 곳으로 갔습니다.
with the aim to design and build a school as my thesis project.
논문 주제가 학교를 기획하고 건축하는 것이었기 때문이었지요.
I had lived in that village before when I was 19 and a volunteer
그 이전인 19세 때 방글라데시의 Dipshikha라는 NGO단체에서
at Dipshikha, a Bangladeshi NGO for rural development.
농촌 개발을 하는 일에 자원봉사로 참여했었습니다.
And what I had learned from them
당시에 제가 알게된 것은
was that the most sustainable strategy for sustainable development
지속 가능한 개발을 위해 가장 중요한 전략이란
is to cherish and to use your very own resources and potential,
지역 고유의 자원과 능력을 소중히 여기고 아끼는 것이며
and not get dependent on external factors.
외부의 자원에 의존하지 않는다는 것이었습니다.
And this is what I tried to do with my architecture as well.
그래서 저는 제 건축물을 세울 때 그 교훈을 적용했지요.
In terms of suitable building materials for my school,
학교를 만드는데 필요한 재료를
I didn't have to look far.
먼 곳에서 찾지 않았습니다.
They were right under my feet:
바로 제 발 아래에 있었지요.
mud, earth, dirt, clay, however you call it ...
진흙, 토양, 흙, 찰흙 등 뭐든지요.
and bamboo that was growing all around.
그리고 사방에는 온통 대나무가 자라고 있었습니다.
Electricity in remote Bangladesh is rare,
방글라데시의 외딴 지역에는 전기가 잘 들어오지 않습니다.
but we didn't need it.
하지만 전기 역시 필요하지 않았지요.
We had human energy
우리에게는 노동력이 있었고
and the people were happy to have the work.
사람들은 기쁜 마음으로 일 할 의지가 있었기 때문입니다.
Tools were an issue, too,
도구 역시 문제가 되었는데요.
but we had these guys,
하지만 우리에게는 이 친구들이 있었죠.
water buffalos.
물소입니다.
We had also tried a bit cows,
우리는 소도 데리고 일하려고 했지만
but interestingly, they were too intelligent.
재미있는 사실을 발견했는데 소들은 너무 똑똑하더군요.
They were always stepping in the holes of the previous round.
소들은 먼저 만들어놓았던 구멍만 밟고 다녀서
They wouldn't mix the mud, the straw --
진흙과 밀짚이 전혀 섞이지 않더라고요.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
the sand, which are the ingredients in the walls.
벽을 만드는데 필요한 재료인 흙도 있었습니다.
And except a small team of consultants
이런 일을 가능하게 해준 제 파트너 에이크 로스워그와
like my partner for realization, Eike Roswag,
자연주의자(basket-weaver)이자 제 사촌인 엠마누엘을 포함한
and my basket-weaver cousin, Emmanuel,
적은 인원의 컨설턴트를 제외하고
it was all built by craftsmen from the village.
그 건물은 마을에 사는 장인들의 수고로 세워졌습니다.
And this is the METI school after six months of construction.
6개월이 걸려 완성된 METI 학교의 모습입니다.
(Applause)
(박수)
Thank you.
감사합니다.
Load-bearing earth walls that really ground the school,
흙으로 만들어진 내력벽으로 학교의 토대를 만들고
and large bamboo structures that bring the lightness in.
큰 대나무로 뼈대를 만들어 빛이 들어오게 했습니다.
That's the classroom on the ground floor.
1층에 있는 교실의 모습입니다.
Attached to it are the caves.
동굴같은 공간이 연결되어 있습니다.
They're for reading, for snuggling, for solo work,
아이들이 책을 읽거나 휴식을 취하거나 혼자 작업할 수 있는 공간이고
for meditation, for playing ...
명상을 하거나 놀이를 할 수 있습니다.
and the classroom on the top.
꼭대기에 있는 교실의 모습입니다.
The children all signed with their names in Bengali the doors,
아이들은 문에 벵갈어로 자신들의 이름을 적었습니다.
and they did not only sign, they also helped building the school.
사실 이름만 적은게 아니라 학교를 짓는데 큰 역할을 했지요.
And I'm sure you all had your hands in mud or clay before.
여러분 모두 진흙이나 점토를 만져본 경험이 있으시죠.
It's wonderful to touch. I love it.
느낌이 참 좋지요. 전 정말 좋아합니다.
The children loved it.
그 아이들 역시 매우 좋아했습니다.
And can you imagine the feeling of a small boy or a girl
어린 아이들과 글도 모르는 노동자들이
or an illiterate day laborer standing in front of that school building
주변에서 흔하게 볼 수 있는 대나무와
and knowing that you built this
발 아래에 있는 흙을 가지고
out of the ordinary bamboo and just the dirt underneath your feet,
자신들의 손으로 세운 이 학교 앞에 설 때면
using nothing but your hands?
기분이 어떨지 상상이 되시나요?
That gives such an enormous boost of trust and confidence
스스로에 대한 신뢰와 자존감이 생겼을 겁니다.
in yourself and the community.
자신들이 사는 지역 사회에 대한 자부심도 느끼겠지요.
And in the material.
이제 재료에 대하여 이야기 해보겠습니다.
Especially mud has a very poor image.
사실 진흙의 이미지는 별로 좋지 않습니다.
When we think of mud, we think of dirt --
진흙을 말하면 우리는 흙을 떠올립니다.
it's ugly, it's nondurable --
흙은 보기에 안좋고 내구성도 없지요.
and this is the image I want to change.
하지만 전 진흙의 이미지를 바꾸고 싶었습니다.
In fact, it's the 11th rainy season for this school now,
실제로 학교는 지금까지 열한 번의 우기를 겪었습니다.
really harsh, horizontal monsoon rains,
매우 세찬 장마비를 맞아야 했습니다.
and the walls are standing strong.
그럼에도 벽은 굳건히 서있습니다.
(Applause)
(박수)
So how does it work?
어떻게 가능했을까요?
First rule, a good foundation that keeps the wall dry from the ground,
첫째, 바닥에서 올라오는 습기로부터 벽을 보호하는 기초공사가 중요합니다.
and second rule, a good roof that protects from the top,
둘째, 꼭대기에서 건물을 보호하는 지붕이 중요하고요.
and third rule, erosion control.
셋째, 침식 방지 장치를 해야합니다.
Mud walls need speed breakers
빗물이 진흙벽을 타고 빠른 속도로 흐르지 않도록
so that the rainwater cannot run down the wall fast,
벽에는 방지턱 같은 장치가 필요합니다.
and these speed breakers could be lines of bamboo
대나무를 붙여놓을 수도 있고
or stones or straw mixed into the mud,
돌과 밀짚을 진흙과 함께 섞을 수도 있습니다.
just like a hill needs trees or rocks in order to prevent erosion.
산에 나무나 바위가 있어야 침식이 일어나지 않는 것과 같은 이치이지요.
It works just the same way.
똑같은 원리입니다.
And people always ask me if I have to add cement to the mud,
사람들은 저에게 항상 시멘트를 진흙에 섞는지 묻습니다.
and the answer is no.
대답은 '아니요' 입니다.
There is no stabilizer, no coating on these walls,
안정제도 넣지 않았고 벽에 코팅도 하지 않았습니다.
only in the foundation.
그런 건 바닥 기초공사에만 사용됩니다.
So this is the close-up of the wall
이것은 열 번의 우기를 겪은 후의
after 10 rainy seasons,
벽의 모습입니다.
and as much as I grew a bit older,
사람이 늙을 때와 마찬가지로
the wall got some wrinkles as well.
벽에도 주름이 생겼지요.
The edges my not be as sharp as before,
가장자리 역시 예전처럼 날렵하진 않아도
but it still looks pretty good,
여전히 괜찮습니다.
and if it needs repairing,
만약 수리할 일이 생기더라도
it is really easy to do.
아주 수월하지요.
You just take the broken part,
부서진 부분을 떼어내고
make it wet, and put it back on the wall,
물에 적신 다음에 다시 벽에 붙이면 됩니다.
and it will look the same as before.
그럼 예전과 별다를 게 없습니다.
Wish that would work on me, too.
사람도 이렇게 고칠 수 있다면 좋겠네요.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
Yeah, and the great thing is,
그리고 큰 장점은
if an earth wall is not needed anymore,
만약 흙으로 만든 벽이 쓸모없게 되면
it can go back to the ground it came from,
원래 있던 땅으로 되돌아갈 수 있다는 점입니다.
turn into a garden,
정원의 흙으로 돌아갈 수도 있고
or get fully recycled without any loss of quality.
재활용되어 쓰여질 수도 있지요.
There's no other material that can do this,
다른 어떤 재료도 이렇게 될 수는 없습니다.
and this is why mud is so excellent in terms of environmental performance.
그래서 진흙은 환경적인 면에서 아주 훌륭한 재료입니다.
What about the economic sustainability?
경제적으로도 지속 가능할까요?
When we built the school,
학교를 세우는 동안
I practically lived on the construction site,
저는 공사장에서 지냈습니다.
and in the evening, I used to go with the workers to the market,
저녁에는 일꾼들과 시장에 종종 함께 가서
and I could see how they spent their money.
그들이 소비하는 방식을 지켜볼 수가 있었습니다.
And they would buy the vegetables from their neighbors,
동네 사람들로부터 야채를 샀고
they would get a new haircut or a new blouse from the tailor.
머리를 하고 새 옷도 샀습니다.
And because the main part of the building budget
건축 예산의 대부분이 그 지역 장인이었던
was spent on craftsmanship,
일꾼들에게 돌아가기 때문에
the school wasn't just a building,
학교는 단지 건축물이 아닌
it became a real catalyst for local development,
지역 사회 발전의 진정한 기폭제가 되었고
and that made me happy.
그래서 저는 정말 기뻤습니다.
If I had designed the school in cement and steel,
만약 제가 시멘트와 철강으로 학교를 지었다면 그 돈은 모두
this money would have been exported and lost for those families.
해외로 빠져 나갔을 것이고 지역 주민의 주머니는 채워지지 않았겠지요.
(Applause)
(박수)
The building budget at that time was 35,000 euros --
당시 건축 비용은 3,6000유로였습니다.
it's probably doubled by now --
지금 비용으로 환산하면 두 배 정도 되겠네요.
and this is a lot of money for that region,
그 지역에서는 큰 돈이었습니다.
and especially because this money is working within the community
그리고 이 돈은 지역 내에서만 유통되고
and rotating fast,
빨리 회전되었으며
and not on the stock market.
주식으로 들어가지도 않았습니다.
So when it comes to the economic sustainability of my project,
따라서 제 프로젝트가 경제적으로도 지속 가능한지에 대한 의문은
my main question is, who gets the profit?
"누구에게 이득인가?" 였습니다.
How many of you in here
여러분 중 진흙으로 만든 집에서
have some experience living in a mud house?
살아본 경험이 있는 분 계시나요?
Chris Anderson, where is your hand?
크리스 앤더슨씨, 손 왜 안드시나요?
(Laughter)
(웃음)
You? OK.
한 분 계시는군요.
Yeah.
네.
It seems totally out of our focus,
우리는 잘 모르고 있지만
but approximately three billion people all around the planet
전 세계 인구 중 약 30억 명이
are living in earth houses,
흙으로 만든 집에서 살고 있고
and it is a traditional building material
아프리카와 마찬가지로 유럽에서도
in Europe just as much as in Africa.
흙은 예로부터 집을 짓는데 사용되었습니다.
Strangely enough,
하지만 이상하게도
mud is not considered worthy of being studied at universities ...
대학에서 진흙은 더이상 연구 대상이 아닙니다.
so I brought the dirt to Harvard,
그래서 저는 흙을 가지고 하버드 대학으로 갔지요.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
precisely 60 tons of dirt right in front of the main facade
정확히 60톤의 흙을 가지고
of the Graduate School of Design.
디자인 대학원 건물 앞으로 갔습니다.
Students and faculty rolled up their sleeves,
학생들과 교직원들은 팔을 걷어 부치고
got their hands dirty
손으로 흙을 만져가며
and transformed the front into a warm place for people to gather.
건물 앞을 사람들이 모일 수 있는 아늑한 장소로 변신시켰습니다.
Children would climb the structures,
아이들은 구조물 위로 올라가기도 했습니다.
skaters would ride the ramp,
스케이트를 타는 사람도 있었고
students having lunch breaks,
점심을 먹고 휴식을 취하는 학생도 있었지요.
and it was particularly fascinating to see how many people were touching the wall,
정말 재미있는 사실은 많은 사람들이 벽을 만지며 지나갔다는 점입니다.
and we usually don't go around cities caressing our facades, right?
사람들은 도시의 건물을 어루만지며 다니진 않잖아요?
(Laughter)
(웃음)
Of course, this was a small-scale project,
물론 이건 작은 프로젝트에 불과하지만
but in terms of awareness-building and in terms of education,
중요성에 대한 인식을 높이고 교육적이라는 면에서 볼 때
it was like an acupuncture trigger point.
시발점이 될 수 있다고 생각합니다.
And in fact, in more and more countries,
그리고 사실 점점 더 많은 나라에서
load-bearing earthen structures are not allowed to be built anymore
흙으로 만드는 내력벽은 더이상 허용되지 않고 있습니다.
although they're traditional and have lasted for hundreds of years,
이것이야말로 전통적인 방법이고 수백 년 동안 내려온 방법인데 말이지요.
and not because the material is weak,
재료 자체가 약해서가 아니고
but because there are no architects and engineers
이 재료를 다룰 수 있는
who know how to deal with that material.
건축가나 기술자가 없기 때문입니다.
So education on all levels,
따라서 장인, 기술자, 건축가들을 위한
for craftsmen, engineers and architects,
다양한 수준의 교육이 필요합니다.
Equally important is technological development,
기술 발달 역시 중요합니다.
like prefabrication developed by my colleague Martin Rauch,
오스트리아 출신으로 흙을 이용해 구조물을 제작하는 전문가이자 예술가인
who is an Austrian artist and expert in earthen structures.
동료인 마틴 라우는 프리패브리케이션 공법을 개발했지요.
And he has created technologies for rammed earth elements,
공장에서 흙다짐 공법으로 미리 벽을 만들고
for prefabrication of rammed earth elements
현장에서 조립하는 기술로
that include insulation, wall heatings and coolings
흙 벽에 단열재, 벽면 냉난방
and all sorts of electrical fittings
그리고 모든 전기 설치가 포함된 기술이지요.
that can be layered to multistoried buildings,
고층 건물을 만들기 위해서 그 벽을 겹겹이 쌓을 수도 있습니다.
and this is important in order to scale up
이것은 건축의 규모가 커지고
and in order to fasten up the processes,
견고한 건물을 만드는데 중요하지요.
like in the Ricola Herb Center in Switzerland.
스위스의 Ricola Herb Center가 하나의 예입니다.
And finally, we need good built projects
그래서 우리는 좋은 프로젝트를 구상해서
that prove you can build with an ancient material
전통적인 건축 재료를 가지고 완전히 현대적인 방식으로
in a very modern way.
건물을 세울 수 있다는 것을 증명하고자 합니다.
It is not a matter of how old a material is;
그 재료가 얼마나 오래된 것인지는 중요하지 않습니다.
it's a matter of our creative ability to use it today.
얼마나 창의적으로 자연 재료를 사용하는지가 중요하지요.
These, for example, are three hostels
예를 들어보겠습니다.
that I did in China in the village Baoxi,
저는 중국의 Baoxi라는 마을에 세 개의 호스텔을 만들었습니다.
about six hours by bus from Shanghai.
상하이에서 버스로 6시간 정도 떨어진 곳이지요.
The outside shape is woven bamboo,
외관은 대나무로 엮었고
and the inside core is stones and rammed earth.
내부는 돌과 굳힌 흙으로 되어 있습니다.
And it is a traditional building material.
전통적인 건축 자재지요.
Even large parts of the Great Wall of China
만리장성도 대부분
have been built with rammed earth,
굳힌 흙으로 지어졌습니다.
but it's getting replaced by concrete.
하지만 계속 콘크리트로 교체되고 있지요.
And this trend is happening very fast.
이 추세는 빠르게 진행되고 있습니다.
Within only a couple of years,
약 2년 내로
China has consumed more cement than the United States
중국이 사용하는 시멘트의 양은
in the entire 20th century.
20세기 통틀어 미국이 사용한 시멘트 양을 추월할 것입니다.
And this trend of replacing natural building materials
이렇게 계속 자연 자원으로 만든 건축물을 교체를 하면
with materials that require a lot of energy,
에너지를 많이 소비합니다.
that are energy-intensive,
에너지 집약적이지요.
and that emit CO2
이산화탄소를 배출하게 되고
is really clearly contributing to climate change.
따라서 지구 온난화의 원인이 됩니다.
And we have alternatives,
우리에게는 또다른 방법이 있잖아요.
such as mud, stones, timber, bamboo, earth,
진흙, 돌, 목재, 대나무, 토양 등,
that are totally effective options for all sorts of purposes.
모두 효과적인 대안이 될 수 있습니다.
This, for example, is an office building that we did
예를 들어 저희는 오스트리아에 Omicron Electronics라는
for Omicron Electronics in Austria.
사무실 건물을 만들었지요.
Mud is healthy for the planet, but also for the human bodies,
진흙을 사용하면 우리가 사는 행성에도 도움이 되지만 우리 몸에도 유익합니다.
and the material is low-tech,
재료는 로우테크(low-tech)지만
but the performance is high-tech.
성과를 보면 하이테크(high tech)지요.
The earth walls keep the highly sophisticated tools in the building safe
안전한 건물을 위한 건축 재료로서 흙으로 만든 벽은 아주 훌륭합니다.
by naturally regulating moisture.
습도를 스스로 조절해서 건물을 유지시키기 때문이지요.
And this wall in my own home
제 집 벽은
is our humidfier.
가습기나 마찬가지고요.
We love our six tons of dirt at home
저희 집에 사용된 6톤의 흙이 정말 마음에 듭니다.
not only because it's healthy and sustainable.
건강하고 지속가능한 재료이기 때문이기도 하지만
Its archaic warmth is touching deep within.
옛 것에서 나오는 따뜻함이 깊은 내면을 어루만저주기 때문입니다.
My personal dream is to build a mud skyscraper right in Manhattan.
저에게는 여기 맨하탄에 진흙 고층 건물을 세우는 꿈이 있습니다.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
Yeah.
네.
(Applause)
(박수)
And this dream isn't so crazy
황당무계한 꿈은 아닙니다.
if you think of the mud city of Shibam in Yemen
예멘에는 시밤이라는 진흙 도시가 있지요.
that was built in the 16th century
16세기에 지어졌고
and has lasted now for 500 years.
지금까지 500년이나 모습이 유지되고 있습니다.
What was possible that long ago is possible today as well,
그 옛날에 가능했던 일은 사실 오늘날에도 가능하지요.
and we can apply all our technical know-how
지금 우리가 가지고 있는 기술적인 노하우를
to these ancient materials
오래전부터 사용해왔던 재료들을 가지고 적용시킬 수 있습니다.
so that it meets our needs and our dreams.
그러면 우리의 꿈이 실현될 것입니다.
All around us,
우리 주변에 있는 모든 것들
and just below our feet ...
그리고 우리 발 바로 아래에 있는 것들
are wonderful natural building materials.
이 모든 것이 건물자재로 사용될 수 있는 훌륭한 자원입니다.
Let's use them.
이것들을 활용합시다.
And I deeply believe
그러면 우리의 집, 일하는 공간
our homes, our work spaces, our cities
우리가 사는 도시가
would become more healthy and sustainable
더 건강해지고 더 지속가능하며
and more humane
더 인간적이고
and beautiful.
더 아름다워질 것입니다.
Thank you.
감사합니다.
(Applause)
(박수)